export const SOCIALSTUDIESA2009 = [

{
id: "question1",
question: "1. When a state is self-sufficient it implies that she",
A: "produces for export",
B: "supports poor countries",
C: "requires limited external help",
D: "needs no external help",
answer: "C. requires limited external help",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question: "2. In Ghana, the following cultural elements bind members of a family together except",
A: "Marriage",
B: "Funerals",
C: "Festivals",
D: "Occupation",
answer: "D. occupation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question: "3. One advantage of practicing democracy in the Ghanaian society is that",
A: "individual rights are protected by law",
B: "people are consulted in all matters",
C: "minority interest is given utmost attention",
D: "the power of the leader is unlimited",
answer: "A. individual rights are protected by law",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question: "4. The sum total of what a person believes to be true about himself/herself is called",
A: "Self-concept",
B: "Self-esteem",
C: "Self-actualization",
D: "Self-confidence",
answer: "A. Self-concept",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question: "5. Which of the following best explains the rights of an individual?",
A: "Basic conditions for social justice",
B: "Claims to which a person is entitled",
C: "The ability to live an independent life",
D: "Legal, moral and value systems",
answer: "B. Claims to which a person is entitled",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question6",
question: "6. The type of leadership which feels that followers do not have any useful ideas is",
A: "Laissez-faire",
B: "Autocratic",
C: "Paternalistic",
D: "Democratic",
answer: "B. Autocratic",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question7",
question: "7. Constitutional democracy is mainly based on",
A: "a sense of accountability",
B: "the supremacy of the legislature",
C: "delegation of powers",
D: "mutual respect for opposing views",
answer: "D. mutual respect for opposing views",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question8",
question: "8. In the Ghanaian society marriage is properly contracted when the",
A: "couple is blessed with children",
B: "couple live peacefully together",
C: "traditional rites have been performed",
D: "man remains head of the family",
answer: "C. traditional rites have been performed",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question9",
question: "9. A major feature of culture is that it is",
A: "natural",
B: "inborn",
C: "dynamic",
D: "static",
answer: "C. Dynamic",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question10",
question: "10. The youthful nature of Ghana’s population implies",
A: "high rate of unemployment",
B: "high cost of medical care",
C: "low fertility rate",
D: "high dependency burden",
answer: "D. high dependency burden",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question11",
question: "11. Siting of development projects in Ghana should be influenced mainly by",
A: "regional considerations",
B: "political expediency",
C: "national interest",
D: "international considerations",
answer: "C. national interest",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question: "12. The Akosombo Dam on the River Volta is an example of",
A: "natural resource",
B: "traditional resource",
C: "human resource",
D: "capital resource",
answer: "D. capital resource",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question13",
question: "13. One benefit derived from formal education is",
A: "preference for white-collar jobs",
B: "making people less superstitious",
C: "adoption of western culture",
D: "strengthening of extended family ties",
answer: "B. making people less superstitious",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question: "14. One of the factors responsible for deforestation is",
A: "bush burning",
B: "mixed farming",
C: "volcanic activity",
D: "dumping of domestic waste",
answer: "A. bush burning",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question15",
question: "15. Which of the following can best help increase productivity?",
A: "Giving all workers equal pay",
B: "Employing more people",
C: "Changing workers tool regularly",
D: "Appropriate skill acquisition by workers",
answer: "D. Appropriate skill acquisition by workers",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question16",
question: "16. Which of the following is not an effect of negative work attitude in the Ghanaian society?",
A: "Inequity in wages",
B: "Loss of time",
C: "Decrease in profit",
D: "Unachieved targets",
answer: "A. Inequity in wages",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question17",
question: "17. The best way of promoting national identity in Ghana is through the",
A: "institution of a common dietary system",
B: "adoption of a common national language",
C: "enforcement of the constitution",
D: "institution of good governance",
answer: "B. adoption of a common national language",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question: "18. Which of the following is not a common cultural practice in Ghana?",
A: "Celebration of festivals",
B: "Celebration of funerals",
C: "Ancestral veneration",
D: "Trokosi system",
answer: "D. Trokosi system",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question19",
question: "19. The purpose of marriage in the Ghanaian society include all the following except",
A: "wealth acquisition",
B: "procreation",
C: "sexual satisfaction",
D: "companionship",
answer: "A. wealth acquisition",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question: "20. In the Ghanaian traditional society the most important value that is inculcated in the child through a naming ceremony is",
A: "Bravery",
B: "Chastity",
C: "Truthfulness",
D: "Obedience",
answer: "C. Truthfulness",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question21",
question: "21. One way the school can help in the socialization process in the Ghanaian society is to teach students",
A: "skills needed for white-collar jobs",
B: "to admire the tenets of of foreign culture",
C: "the importance of acquiring academic knowledge",
D: "traditional skills in farming, fishing and craftwork",
answer: "D. traditional skills in farming, fishing and craftwork",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question: "22. Which of the following is an agency of socialization?",
A: "The sister",
B: "The family",
C: "The mother",
D: "The father",
answer: "B. The family",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question23",
question: "23. The best way of preventing deviant behaviour in society is to encourage",
A: "compulsory religious education",
B: "peer pressure",
C: "parental love and control",
D: "corporal punishment",
answer: "C. parental love and control",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question24",
question: "24. Which of the following is not symbolized by the national flag of Ghana",
A: "Ghanaian hospitality",
B: "Mineral wealth",
C: "The vegetation",
D: "The blood of the forefathers",
answer: "A. Ghanaian hospitality",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question25",
question: "25. One characteristic of the Commonwealth is that its members have",
A: "a common historical background",
B: "advanced democratic institutions",
C: "high economic development",
D: "internal peace and stability",
answer: "A. a common historical background",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question26",
question: "26. The foundation of technology is",
A: "practical training",
B: "social research",
C: "scientific knowledge",
D: "critical thinking",
answer: "C. scientific knowledge",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question27",
question: "27. The provision of infrastructure such as roads, electricity and industries constitute",
A: "political development",
B: "population growth",
C: "social growth",
D: "economic development",
answer: "D. economic development",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question28",
question: "28. Involving workers in decision making at the workplace ensures",
A: "easy access to work",
B: "commitment to work",
C: "satisfaction of their needs",
D: "high staff turnover",
answer: "B. commitment to work",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question: "29. Positive attitudes usually expected from employees include the following except",
A: "discipline and a high sense of duty",
B: "allowing the employer to take all decision",
C: "trustworthiness, truthfulness and fairness",
D: "regard for employer’s property",
answer: "B. allowing the employer to take all decisions",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question30",
question: "30. In which sector of the economy does the manufacturing of goods into semi-finished products fall?",
A: "Primary sector",
B: "Public sector",
C: "Tertiary sector",
D: "Secondary sector",
answer: "D. Secondary sector",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question31",
question: "31. Which of the following group of people are considered as the custodians of the traditions of land?",
A: "Linguists",
B: "Elders",
C: "Chiefs",
D: "Ancestors",
answer: "C. Chiefs",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question: "32. In a society the enjoyment of rights must go with authority privileges considerations responsibilities",
A: "**********",
B: "**********",
C: "**********",
D: "**********",
answer: "D. responsibilities",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question: "33. During elections in Ghana, the people exercise their",
A: "political rights",
B: "natural rights",
C: "economic rights",
D: "legal rights",
answer: "A. political rights",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question: "34. The following are functions of the judicial organ of government in the Ghanaian society except",
A: "dispensation of justice",
B: "settlement of disputes",
C: "interpretation of the law",
D: "proposition of new laws",
answer: "D. proposition of new laws",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question: "35. Inheritance acquired through the mother’s line of descent is called",
A: "Matrilineal",
B: "Heredity",
C: "Patrilineal",
D: "Lineage",
answer: "A. Matrilineal",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question: "36. A business can best be sustained by",
A: "employing more people",
B: "producing more goods",
C: "producing quality goods",
D: "making huge profit",
answer: "C. producing quality goods",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question: "37. The most important factor in the production of goods and services is",
A: "capital",
B: "labour",
C: "land",
D: "the entrepreneur",
answer: "D. the entrepreneur",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question38",
question: "38. In Ghana, the highest political authority is the",
A: "Judiciary",
B: "Electorate",
C: "Legislature",
D: "President",
answer: "D. President",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question: "39. Which of the following can best check dictatorship in the state?",
A: "Free legal services",
B: "Freedom of association",
C: "The right to vote",
D: "Separation of powers",
answer: "D. Separation of powers",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question40",
question: "40. The ultimate aim of national development is to promote a higher quality of life ensure food security for the people enrich the traditional values of a people concentrate wealth in the hands of fewer people",
},

{
id: "question41",
question: "41. In Ghana low saving is mainly attributed to low incomes and high",
A: "foreign exchange rate",
B: "dependency ratio",
C: "national debt",
D: "population growth",
answer: "B. dependency ratio",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question42",
question: "42. Which of the following leadership styles allows greater freedom to followers?",
A: "Democratic",
B: "Paternalistic",
C: "Laissez-faire",
D: "Autocratic",
answer: "C. Laissez-faire",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question: "43. The minimum number of persons required to form a partnership is",
A: "Two",
B: "Three",
C: "Four",
D: "Five",
answer: "A. Two",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question: "44. The inability to sufficiently exploit and utilize natural resources is due mainly to",
A: "lack of technical know how",
B: "poor management practices",
C: "poor attitude to work",
D: "high cost of living",
answer: "A. lack of technical know-how",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question: "45. In the Ghanaian society bye-laws are passed by",
A: "Local Authorities",
B: "The Courts",
C: "The Executive",
D: "Parliament",
answer: "A. Local Authorities",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question: "46. One reason why sole proprietorship is a common business unit in Ghana is that",
A: "has limited liability",
B: "has a legal status",
C: "is easy to make decisions",
D: "has a long life-span",
answer: "C. is easy to make decisions",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question: "47. Self-confidence can be built through",
A: "Self-denial",
B: "Self-actualization",
C: "Self-defence",
D: "self-determination",
answer: "D. self-determination",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question: "48. The main source of environmental pollution from the home is the use of firewood use of gas use of insecticide disposal of garbage",
},

{
id: "question49",
question: "49. The main weakness of Knowledge-based education in Ghana is the inadequate",
A: "preparation for leadership",
B: "acquisition of skills",
C: "acquisition of traditional values",
D: "preparation for family responsibilities",
answer: "B. acquisition of skills",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question: "50. The purpose of establishing foster homes is to",
A: "maintain children with no parental love and care",
B: "provide maintenance for handicapped children",
C: "create families for children who are abused",
D: "create second homes for brilliant but needy children",
answer: "A. maintain children with no parental love and care",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question51",
question: "51. The main objective of social development is to improve upon the people’s",
A: "standard of living",
B: "technological skills",
C: "economic skills",
D: "educational standards",
answer: "A. standard of living",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question52",
question: "52. The most important benefit of family planning is that it",
A: "eliminates infant diseases",
B: "reduces the occurrence of redundant labour",
C: "increases population growth in society",
D: "increases financial resources of society",
answer: "D. increases financial resources of society",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question53",
question: "53. One of the characteristics of informal education is that it",
A: "uses unstructured forms of teaching",
B: "helps its students to read and write",
C: "is scientific in its approach",
D: "has specially trained teachers",
answer: "A. uses unstructured forms of teaching",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question54",
question: "54. Misunderstandings in the Ghanaian traditional society are best addressed by",
A: "the traditional priest",
B: "the Chief Linguist",
C: "legal and moral codes",
D: "sociocultural practices",
answer: "D. sociocultural practices",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question55",
question: "55. All these factors can hinder development except",
A: "low saving capacity of the individual",
B: "low capital accumulation",
C: "high standard of living",
D: "high cost of living",
answer: "C. high standard of living",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question56",
question: "56. Generally, a person who is not of sound mind is disqualified from",
A: "belonging to a family",
B: "being considered a Ghanaian citizen",
C: "contesting elections",
D: "receiving legal services",
answer: "C. contesting elections",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question57",
question: "57. Parents have the responsibility of providing the following for their children  \nI.	health needs  \nII.	nutritional needs  \nIII.	personal vision  \nIV.	Self-confidence",
A: "I, II and III only",
B: "I and II only",
C: "II and IV only",
D: "I, II and IV only",
answer: "B. I and II only",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question58",
question: "58. Farmers in Ghana do not benefit fully from the services provided by extension officers because",
A: "most farmers are conservative",
B: "of the hostile attitude of farmers",
C: "the cost of extension services is high",
D: "the officers do not visit the farms often",
answer: "A. most farmers are conservative",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question59",
question: "59. The attitude that can best increase productivity in a government organization is",
A: "seeing yourself as a stakeholder",
B: "encouraging overtime work",
C: "reporting lazy workers to management",
D: "working according to the salary you earn",
answer: "A. seeing yourself as a stakeholder",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question60",
question: "60. The capabilities of a person are most effectively harnessed through",
A: "Education",
B: "Motivation",
C: "Socialization",
D: "Indoctrination",
answer: "A. Education",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},



]